[Music]
Reedman reads
The Giver by Lois Lowry, narrated by Fraser Reedman.
Chapter 19.
Jonas glanced at the clock.. There was so much work to be done, always, that he and
The Giver seldom simply sat and talked, the way they just had..
"I'm sorry that I wasted so much time with my questions,". Jonas said., ""I was
only asking about release because my father is releasing a new child today., A
twin.. He has to select one and release the other one.. They do it by weight."."
Jonas glanced at the clock.. "Actually,, I suppose he's already finished.. I think
it was this morning.". The givers's face took on a solemn look..
""I wish they wouldn't do that,"," he said quietly,, almost to himself.. ""Well,, they
can't have two identical people around!.
Think how confusing it would be!"," Jonas chuckled.. ""I wish I could watch,"," he
added, as an afterthought.. He liked the thought of seeing his father perform the
ceremony, and making the little twin clean and comfy.. His father was such a
gentle man.. ""You can watch,"," The Giver said.. ""No,"," Jonas told They never let
children watch.. It's very private.".
"Jonas,", The Giver told him,, ""I know that you read your training instructions very
carefully.. Don't you remember that you are allowed to ask anyone anything?"?"
Jonas nodded.. ""Yes,, but—" "Jonas,, when you and I have finished our time together,,
you will be the new Receiver.. You can read the books;. you'll have the
memories.. You have access to everything..
It's part of your training.. If you want to watch a release,, you simply have to
ask. Jonah shrugged..
"Well,, maybe I will, then., But it's too late for this one.. I'm sure it was this
morning.". The Giver told him, then,, something he had not known..
"All private ceremonies are recorded..
They're in the Hall of Closed Records..
Do you want to see this morning's release??
Jonas hesitated.. He was afraid that his father wouldn't like it, if he watched
something so private.. "I think you should,", The Giver told him firmly.. "All
right,, then. Jonah said., "Tell me how.".
The Giver rose from his chair,, went to the speaker on the wall,, and click the
switch from OFF to ON.. The voice spoke immediately..
"Yes,, Receiver.. How may I help you?"?
"I would like to see this morning's release of the twin.".
"One moment,, Receiver.. Thank you for your instructions.".
Jonas watched the video screen above the row of switches.. Its blank face began to
flicker with zigzag lines;. then some numbers appeared,, followed by the date
and time.. He was astonished and delighted that this was available to him,
and surprised that he had not known..
Suddenly, he could see a small windowless room, empty except for a bed,,
a table with some equipment on it—. —Jonas recognized a scale;. he had seen them
before, when he'd been doing volunteer hours at the Nurturing Center—, and a
cupboard.. He could see pale carpeting on the floor.. "It's just an ordinary room,",
he commented..
"I thought maybe they'd have it in the Auditorium, so that everybody could come..
All the Old go to Ceremonies of Release., But I suppose that when it's just a
newborn,, they don't. Sh, The Giver said,, his eyes on the screen.. Jonas's father,,
wearing his nurturing uniform,, entered the room,, cradling a tiny new child
wrapped in a soft blanket in his arms..
A uniformed woman followed through the door,, carrying a second new child
wrapped in a similar blanket.. ""That's my father."," Jonas found himself whispering,,
as if he might wake the little ones if he spoke aloud..
"And the other Nurturer is his assistant..
"She's still in training,, but she'll be finished soon."." The two Nurturers
unwrapped the blankets and laid the identical newborns on the bed.. They were
naked.. Jonas could see that they were males.. He watched,, fascinated,, as his
father gently lifted one, then the other to the scale and weighed them.. He heard
his father laugh.. ""Good,"," his father said to the woman.. ""I thought for a
moment that they might both be exactly the same.. Then we'd have a problem.. But
this one,"," he handed one, after rewrapping it, to his assistant,. ""is six
even., So you can clean him up and dress him and take him over to the Center."."
The woman took the new child and left through the door she had entered.. Jonas
watched as his father bent over the squirming new child on the bed.. ""And
you,, little guy,, you're only 5 lb 10 o, A shrimp!." ""That's the special voice he
uses with Gabriel,"," Jonas remarked,, smiling.. ""Watch,"," The Giver said.. ""Now
he cleans him up and makes him comfy,"."
Jonas told him., ""He told me."." ""Be quiet,, Jonas,"." The Giver commanded in a strange
voice.. "Watch.." Obediently, Jonas concentrated on the screen,, waiting for
what would happen next.. He was especially curious about the ceremony
part.. His father turned and opened the cupboard..
He took out a syringe and a small bottle.. Very carefully, he inserted the
needle into the bottle and began to fill the syringe with a clear liquid.. Jonas
winced sympathetically..
He had forgotten that new children had to get shots.. He hated shots himself,,
though he knew that they were necessary..
To his surprise,, his father began very carefully to direct the needle into the
top of new child's forehead,, puncturing the place where the fragile skin pulsed..
The newborn squirmed, and wailed faintly.
"Why is he?" "Sh," The Giver said sharply..
His father was talking,, and Jonas realized that he was hearing the answer
to the question he had started to ask..
Still in the special voice,, his father was saying,, ""I know,, I know. It hurts,,
little guy., But I have to use a vein,, and the veins in your arms are still too
teeny weeny." He pushed the plunger very slowly,, injecting the liquid into the
scalp vein until the syringe was empty..
""All done.. That wasn't so hard, was it?"?"
Jonas heard his father say cheerfully..
He turned aside and dropped the syringe into a waste recepticle. Now he cleans
him up and makes him comfy,," Jonas said to himself,, aware that The Giver didn't
want to talk during the little ceremony..
As he continued to watch,, the new child, no longer crying,, moved his arms and
legs in a jerking motion, and he went limp. His head fell to the side,, his
eyes half open..
Then he was still..
With an odd,, shocked feeling,, Jonas recognized the gestures and posture and
expression.. They were familiar.. He had seen them before., But he couldn't
remember where.. Jonas stared at the screen,, waiting for something to happen.,
But nothing did.. The little twin lay motionless..
His father was putting things away., Folding the blanket., Closing the
cupboard.. Once again,, as he had on the playing field,, he felt the choking
sensation.. Once again, he saw the face of the light-haired, bloodied soldier.
as life left his eyes., The memory came back.. He killed it!. My father killed it,"
Jonah said to himself,, stunned at what he was realizing.. He continued to stare
at the screen numbly.. His father tidied the room.. Then he picked up a small
carton that lay waiting on the floor,, set it on the bed, and lifted the limp
body into it.. He placed the lid on tightly.. He picked up the carton and
carried it to the other side of the room.. He opened a small door in the wall;.
Jonas could see darkness behind the door.. It seemed to be the same sort of
chute into which trash was deposited at school.. His father loaded the carton
containing the body into the chute and gave it a shove.. "Bye-bye,, little guy,".
Jonas heard his father say before he left the room..
Then the screen went blank..
The Giver turned to him. Quite calmly,. he related,. "When the Speaker notified me
that Rosemary had applied for release,, they turned on the tape to show me the process..
There she was—, —my last glimpse of that beautiful child— —waiting.. They brought in
the syringe and asked her to roll up her sleeve.. "You suggested,, Jonas,, that
perhaps she wasn't brave enough?. I don't know about bravery:. what it is,, what it means..
I do know that I sat here numb with horror., Wretched with helplessness.,
And I listened as Rosemary told them that she would prefer to inject herself.
"And she did so.." I didn't watch.. I looked away.". The Giver turned to him.
"there you are,, Jonas.. You are wondering about release,"," he said in a bitter
voice.. Jonas felt a ripping sensation inside himself, a feeling of terrible
pain clawing its way forward to emerge in a cry.
[Music]